Guide to the Marshall Bond Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Marshall Bond papers
1869-1976
WA MSS S-2358
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
2.21
7 boxes
The papers document the life, work, and adventures of Marshall Bond between 1897 and 1935, and also include a few papers of his father, Hiram G. Bond, and his son, Marshall Bond, Jr. Bond's Klondike experience is well documented by his diary from 1897-98, letters to his family, draft chapters of a memoir about his experiences, and photographs. The photographs include one of the dog who inspired Jack London's novel The Call of the Wild; several of the Bond family's California home, on which London based the setting for the beginning of the novel; and forty-five commercially produced photos of the Klondike region and Dawson by E. A. Hegg and other photographers. The bulk of the collection is correspondence, which includes Bond's letters to his family from the Klondike, from Goldfield, Nevada in 1904, from Mexican villages under attack by Pancho Villa in 1918, and from hunting trips in Alaska in 1911 and Africa in 1927. It also includes his incoming and outgoing correspondence with business associates and friends, which documents mining ventures and other matters, including a plan to settle Boer refugees in Mexico. Bond's letters to Herbert H. White report intelligence about Germans in the American Southwest during World War I. The correspondence includes one letter from Jack London to Marshall Bond, in which London confirms that the character "Buck" was indeed based on the Bonds' dog, and Judge Miller's house in the novel on Judge Bond's house in Santa Clara. The collection also includes photographs taken in 1926 of surviving associates of Billy the Kid, a few World War I letters from the front, copies of newspaper articles by Bond, maps of the Yukon Territory, and a typescript of a book by Marshall Bond, Jr.
Other Storage Formats: 2 broadside folders
Bond, Marshall, 1867-1941
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Richard M. and Marshall Bond, Jr., 1952-1976
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Restricted Fragile material in box 7 may be consulted only with permission of the appropriate curator. Preservation photocopies for reference use have been substituted in the main files.
MARSHALL BOND
Marshall Bond (1867-1941) was born in Richmond, Virginia, the second son of Federal Judge Hiram G. Bond and Laura Higgins Bond. The family moved to Denver, Colorado in 1870, and therafter continued to relocate frequently to be near the Judge's mining investments and other business concerns. Marshall Bond attended St. Paul's School, in New Hampshire, and Yale College, graduating in 1888.
After college, he worked for his father's mining company in Seattle and formed a real estate partnership with Oliver H. P. La Farge. In July of 1897, Marshall Bond, his brother Louis Bond, La Farge, and Stanley Pearce left Seattle for the Klondike gold rush, settling in Dawson City, Northwest Territories for the winter of 1897-98. There, the Bond brothers befriended Jack London, who later based The Call of the Wild on Louis Bond's dog Jack and used New Park, Judge Bond's home in Santa Clara, California, as the setting for the beginning of the novel.
Although his Klondike venture was not profitable, Bond continued to work in gold mining for most of his life, investing in claims independently and with various business partners, working as a special correspondent to several West coast newspapers from Goldfield, Nevada in 1904-05, and as a consultant to mining companies, including the Alvarado Mining and Milling Company in Chihuahua, Mexico, during a period of raids by Pancho Villa in 1918. His last mining interest was in the Mohave desert in the 1930s. At other times he worked as director of his father's companies and as a stockbroker, and seems to have served as a domestic intelligence agent during World War I. Other projects included an official visit to Mexico City in 1902 with Boer General W. D. Snyman to discuss the permanent relocation of Boer refugees to Mexico.
Bond was an avid adventurer and big game hunter. In addition to regular camping trips with friends and family, he went on at least two major hunting expeditions: one on the Stikine River in Alaska in 1911, the other an extended trip through Africa in 1927.
Marshall Bond married Amy Louise Burnett of Seattle. They had two children: Richard M. Bond, born in 1903, and Marshall Bond, Jr., born in 1908. Both sons are Yale graduates.
Scope and Contents
The Marshall Bond Papers document the life of gold miner and adventurer Marshall Bond (1867-1941), and his family. The papers span the years 1869-1976, with the bulk falling between 1897 and 1935. The papers are organized into four series: Correspondence, Writings, Other Papers, and Photographs.
Series I, Correspondence, is organized into two subseries: Family Correspondence and Other Correspondence. The first, Family Correspondence, contains letters to and from Bond family members. It is arranged chronologically, and consists chiefly of long, detailed letters from Marshall Bond to his parents, his wife, and his sons. The most extensive group are letters written from the Klondike in 1897-98. Other letters from Bond to his family document a brief trip to Manila in 1899; his trip to Mexico in 1902 with E. Reeve Merritt and Boer General W. D. Synman; his experiences in Goldfield, Nevada, during the mining boom there in 1904; the Pancho Villa attacks on villages in Chihuahua, Mexico in 1918; and his tour through Africa in 1927. Other family correspondence includes a letter to Bond from his father, letters from his nephew Marshall Bond regarding a mining venture, and letters from cousins, including two letters from a cousin serving at the front in France during World War I. Also included in this subseries is a letter to Marshall Bond, Jr., from his cousin Edward Bond, Louis Bond's son, which contains a transcription of a letter from Jack London to Louis Bond, and of London's inscription in Louis Bond's copy of Call of the Wild.
Other Correspondence consists of letters written by non family members to Marshall Bond, Hiram G. Bond, Louis W. and Mary Bond, and Marshall Bond, Jr., as well as a few letters written to other parties. This subseries is arranged alphabetically under headings for each recipient. It consists chiefly of letters to Marshall Bond from business associates and friends, but also includes letters written to and on behalf of his father, Judge Hiram G. Bond, regarding a federal judgeship appointment in 1869, copies of letters from Mrs. Jack London to Louis and Mary Bond, and one letter to Marshall Bond, Jr., from his father's friend Osborne Beauclerk, Duke of St. Albans. Copies of Marshall Bond's outgoing correspondence can be found throughout this subseries, interfiled with incoming letters from each correspondent. The letters to Marshall Bond document his mining investments and consultant work, other business ventures, and the plan to settle the Boers in Mexico in 1902, as well as his friendships with classmates from Yale and St. Paul's, business partners and associates, adventurers such as Warburton Pike and Belmore Browne, and writer Jack London. There is one letter from Jack London to Marshall Bond in the collection, in which London confirms that "Buck" in The Call of the Wild was indeed based on the Bonds' dog. The most substantial files in this subseries are those of Bond's correspondence with Richard M. Hurd, Oliver H. P. La Farge, George H. Mairs, Robert Rea, A. P. Rogers, and Lady Glover. Correspondence with Herbert H. White concerns Bond's role as an intelligence agent in an unnamed organization during World War I. Third party correspondence includes two letters from the Klondike in 1898 written by a man named Charlie, a typescript of a World War I letter from A. B. E. Cator, and copies of letters concerning Warburton Pike.
Series II, Writings, includes Bond's diary from the Klondike in 1897-98 and draft chapters of an uncompleted book about his Klondike experience; clippings of newspaper articles he wrote about the gold rush in Goldfield, Nevada, and Idaho in 1902-5 and about Pancho Villa in 1918; and a typescript carbon of his diary from his hunting trip on the Stikine River in 1911. Other writings include a short story about Africa, which accompanies a letter and is stored with the letter in Series I, and pages of his diary documenting a 1926 trip with New Mexico Governor Miguel Otero to interview surviving associates of Billy the Kid in Lincoln County, New Mexico, which are in his photo album from that trip, in Series IV.
Series III, Other Papers, includes a contract between Marshall Bond and L. W. Fox of Dawson City in 1897, witnessed by Jack London and Louis Bond; maps of the Yukon Territory and Alaska; a copy of a mine report; and an essay by Oliver H. P. La Farge about a camping trip he took with the Bonds. Also present is a bound typescript of a book by Marshall Bond, Jr., Adventures with Peons, Princes and Tycoons, with photographs tipped in (this book was later published by Star Rover House, 1983).
Series IV, Photographs, contains one photograph of Marshall Bond in his undergraduate years at Yale; forty-five commercially produced photographs of Dawson City and the Klondike region, the majority of them by Eric A. Hegg, with a few by Larss and Duclos, one by Case and Draper, and one by M. Craig; two personal photographs of the Bonds' cabin in Dawson and its inhabitants, one of which includes the dog that inspired Jack London's The Call of the Wild; photographs of Judge Bond and his wife Laura, Louis and Mary Bond and their children, and Marshall and Amy Bond with their son Richard in 1906 at New Park, the Judge's Santa Clara house on which London based the setting of the beginning of The Call of the Wild, as well as photos of the interior and exterior of the house itself; a portrait of Marshall Bond with Boer General W. D. Snyman and E. Reeve Merritt taken in Mexico City during their official visit on behalf of Boer refugees in 1902; snapshots of the Goldfield, Nevada mines, miners, and the Bond family's cabin there in 1904; two photos of miners in Jarbridge, Nevada in 1910; and a studio portrait of Marshall Bond in middle-age.
There are also two photo albums in this series. One documents Bond's hunting trip on the Stikine River in Alaska in 1911, and includes photos of Warburton Pike, Lord Osborne Beauclerk (later Duke of St. Albans), and Bond's older son Richard. The other album documents a trip Bond took in 1926 with his son Marshall, New Mexico Governor Miguel Otero, and Mrs. Otero to interview surviving associates of Billy the Kid; it includes pictures of Frank and George Coe and their wives, Susan E. (McSween) Barber, and others. Also present are loose commercial reproductions of photos of Billy the Kid and other Wild West figures such as the James Gang.
Afrikaners -- Mexico -- History; Big game hunting; Gold mines and mining -- Alaska; Gold mines and mining -- Idaho; Gold mines and mining -- Mexico; Gold mines and mining -- Nevada; Gold mines and mining -- Yukon -- Klondike River Valley; Miners; Silver mines and mining -- Mexico; World War, 1914-1918 -- Intelligence service; Africa -- Description and travel; Alaska -- Description and travel; Alaska -- Gold discoveries; Chihuahua (Mexico: State) -- History; Dawson (Yukon); Goldfield (Nev.); Klondike River Valley (Yukon) -- Description and travel; Klondike River Valley (Yukon) -- Gold discoveries; Lincoln County (N.M.) -- History; Mexico -- Description and travel; Mexico -- Foreign relations -- South Africa; Mexico -- History -- Revolution, 1910-1920; Southwest, New -- History -- 1848-; Stikine River (B.C. and Alaska) -- Description and travel; Diaries; Gold rush diaries; Maps (documents); Photograph albums; Photographic prints; Billy, the Kid, 1859-1881; Bond, Amy K.; Bond, Hiram Gilbert, 1838-1906; Bond, Louis W.; Bond, Marshall, 1867-1941; Bond, Marshall; Bond, Marshall ( Adventures with peons, princes and tycoons); Bond, Richard M.; Brown, Belmore, 1880-1954; Carter, George Robert, 1866-1933; Hegg, Eric A., 1867-1948; Hurd, Richard M. (Richard Melancthon), 1865-1941; La Farge, Oliver H. P.; Langford, George; London, Charmian, 1871-1955; London, Jack, 1876-1916 ( Call of the wild); Mairs, George H.; Pike, Warburton, 1861-1915; Pomeroy, Daniel Eleazer, 1868-1965; Rea, Robert; Rives, A. L.; Rogers, Alexander P.; Snyman, W. D.; St. Albans, Osborne de Vere Beauclerk; Train, Arthur, 1875-1945; Villa, Pancho, 1878-1923; Waring, Guy, 1859?-1936; White, Herbert
- Correspondence, 1869-1962; Series I; 0.84; (2 boxes)
  Scope and Contents
  This series is organized into two subseries: Family Correspondence and Other Correspondence.
  - FAMILY CORRESPONDENCE
    This subseries is organized under two headings: Marshall Bond and Marshall Bond, Jr. It is arranged chronologically.
    - Marshall Bond
      - MB to his parents and to his wife Amy Burnett Bond from the Klondike, 1897-98 (Box 1, Folder 1)
        Typed carbon transcripts accompany some of the letters
      - MB to ABB, from Manila, 1899 Oct 9 (Box 1, Folder 2)
      - Hiram G. Bond to MB, 1901 Nov 17 (Box 1, Folder 3)
      - MB to ABB from Idaho, 1902 Apr 5 (Box 1, Folder 4)
      - MB to ABB from Mexico, 1902 Oct (Box 1, Folder 5)
      - MB to ABB from Goldfield, Nevada, 1904 Aug 17 (Box 1, Folder 6)
      - Esther Gardner [cousin] to MB, [1905?] Apr 13 (Box 1, Folder 7)
      - MB to ABB from Dease Lake, B.C. (photocopy), 1911 Aug 22 (Box 1, Folder 8)
      - MB to ABB and sons from Mexico, regarding Pancho Villa, 1918 Sep (Box 1, Folder 9)
        Letter of Sep 25 encloses a photograph of Villa, Trilla, and Morales
      - Parton Swift [cousin] to MB, 2 ALS from France, with photograph and postcard, 1918 Nov (Box 1, Folder 10)
      - MB to ABB and sons, TLS, and 2 carbon copies of typed letters to son Dick, 1919-24 (Box 1, Folder 11)
      - MB to ABB and MB Jr. from Africa, 1927 (Box 1, Folder 12)
        Letter of Apr 28 encloses typescript carbon of story by MB, "Bmali of the Lurio"
      - MB to ABB from New York City, 1930 Jul 12 (Box 1, Folder 13)
      - MB correspondence with Marshall Bond, Esq. [nephew], 1934 (Box 1, Folder 14)
      - MB to MB, Jr., 1934-36 (Box 1, Folder 15)
      - Parton Swift to MB, 1935 Aug 30 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Marshall Bond, Jr.
      - Edward L. Bond to MB Jr., containing transcript of Jack London letter and inscription to Louis W. Bond, 1907-08, 1962 Nov 3 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - OTHER CORRESPONDENCE
    This subseries is organized under five headings: Hiram G. Bond, Louis W. and Mary Bond, Marshall Bond, Marshall Bond, Jr., and Third Party Correspondence. The headings and the correspondence under each are arranged alphabetically. Copies of Marshall Bond's outgoing correspondence can be found throughout.
    - Hiram G. Bond
      - Rives, Alexander to HGB, 1869 Mar 26 (Box 1, Folder 18)
      - Letters of recommendation for U. S. Circuit Judgeship in Richmond, Virginia, 1869 Apr-Aug (Box 1, Folder 19)
        To President Grant from various colleagues; to Major General Canby from Alex Rives and H. H. Wells
    - Louis W. and Mary Bond
      - London, Charmian Kittredge [Mrs. Jack London], photocopies of three letters, 1907 (Box 1, Folder 20)
      - London, Jack [transcription], 1907-08
        Related Archival Materials note
        See: box 1, folder 17
    - Marshall Bond
      - American Engineering and Operating Company (Alvarado Mining and Milling), George Millar and A. W. Morris, 1919 (Box 1, Folder 21)
      - Beauclerk, Osborne [Duke of St. Albans] (photocopy), 1915-20 (Box 1, Folder 22)
      - Boone and Crockett Club, signed Kermit Roosevelt, 1923-36 (Box 1, Folder 23)
      - Browne, Belmore, [1924] (Box 1, Folder 24)
      - Bronimann, Emilio, 1919 Nov 8 (Box 1, Folder 25)
      - Canada Geological Survey, 1923 Jul 17 (Box 1, Folder 26)
      - Carrell, William A., 1929-30 (Box 1, Folder 27)
      - Carter, George R., 1917-23 (Box 1, Folder 28)
      - Duane, William North, copy of outgoing letter only, 1926 Jan 30 (Box 1, Folder 29)
      - F general, 1923-34 (Box 1, Folder 30)
      - Glover, Lady, 1915-21 (Box 1, Folder 31)
        Letter of 1916 Mar 9 encloses clipping "Women and Farm Work: Object Lesson from France"
      - H general, 1914-22 (Box 1, Folder 32)
      - Herter, Adele, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 33)
      - Hunt, Leigh, 1921-23 (Box 1, Folder 34)
      - Hurd, Richard M., 1916-35 (Box 1, Folder 35)
      - Kelleher, Daniel and Elise, 1920 (Box 2, Folder 36)
      - La Farge, Oliver H. P., 1919-26 (Box 2, Folder 37)
      - Langford, George, 1923 (Box 2, Folder 38)
        With carbon copy of letter from Franklin Wheaton Smith to Langford
      - Lavell Gold Mining Company, 1919 (Box 2, Folder 39)
      - Little, Brown, and Co., 1934 Oct 24 (Box 2, Folder 40)
      - London, Jack, 1903 Dec 17 (Box 2, Folder 40a)
      - Mairs, George H., 1914-26 (Box 2, Folder 41)
      - Marston, Fred, 1919 (Box 2, Folder 42)
      - Merritt, Reeve, 1921 (Box 2, Folder 43)
      - Nora, copy of outgoing only, regarding Joseph Grafton Minot, 1939 Jun 22 (Box 2, Folder 44)
      - P general, 1918-34 (Box 2, Folder 45)
      - Penton, John A., 1934 (Box 2, Folder 46)
        With copies of three reports to Penton from E. C. Barringer
      - Pike, Warburton and Marmaduke, with obituaries of Warburton Pike (photocopies), 1912-15 (Box 2, Folder 47)
      - Pomeroy, Daniel E., 1921 Apr (Box 2, Folder 48)
      - Ratibor, Egon, 1916 (Box 2, Folder 49)
      - Rea, Robert, 1919 (Box 2, Folder 50)
      - Richards, W. P., 1919-20 (Box 2, Folder 51)
      - Ripley, Thomas E., 1933-34 (Box 2, Folder 52)
      - Rogers, Alexander P., 1919 (Box 2, Folder 53)
      - S general, 1919-33 (Box 2, Folder 54)
      - Scarborough, O. C., 1919 (Box 2, Folder 55)
      - Smith, Franklin Wheaton, 1920-35 (Box 2, Folder 56)
      - Snyman, W. D. and Hardus, 1915-16 (Box 2, Folder 57)
        With telegram from Frank L. Peckham informing MB of General Snyman's death
      - Somers [or Somerwell?], from Italy, 1934-38 (Box 2, Folder 58)
      - Townsend, Mary [Mrs. George], n.y. Aug 4 (Box 2, Folder 59)
      - Train, Arthur Cheney, 1922-27 (Box 2, Folder 60)
      - Warburg, James P., 1934 Oct 1 (Box 2, Folder 61)
      - Waring, Guy, 1922-23 (Box 2, Folder 62)
        One letter is written on the verso of a letter from La Farge to Waring
      - White, Herbert H., 1917-18 (Box 2, Folder 63)
        Existence and Location of Copies
        Preservation photocopies provided for fragile originals; digital versions also available for the items linked above.
      - Wodehouse, Norman, 1921-22 (Box 2, Folder 64)
    - Marshall Bond, Jr.
      - Beauclerk, Osborne [Duke of St. Albans], 1954 Aug 7 (Box 2, Folder 65)
    - Third Party Correspondence
      - Beauclerk, Osborne [Duke of St. Albans] to C. Karl Coudenhove, regarding Warburton Pike (photocopy), 1915 Dec 21 (Box 2, Folder 66)
      - Byam, Dr., typed copies of letters from R. Slatin and E. A. Stanton, and printed Christmas card from the Byams, 1926-27 (Box 2, Folder 67)
      - Cator, A. B. E., to unknown recipient, typescript carbon, regarding World War I battle, 1914 Oct 27 (Box 2, Folder 68)
      - Charlie, 2 ALS to May, from Dawson City, 1898-99 (Box 2, Folder 69)
      - Hunter, Fenley, TLS to Colonel W. L. Hallahan, regarding Warburton Pike monument at Dease Lake, 1956 Mar 15 (Box 2, Folder 70)
      - Little, Archie to H. H. Webb, carbon copy of typed letter, 1933 Sep 4 (Box 2, Folder 71)
- Writings, 1897-1927; Series II; 0.4; (1 box)
  Arranged in chronological order of the events described.
  - Klondike diary, 1897-98 (Box 3, Folder 72)
  - Klondike diary chronology, manuscript and draft narrative fragment (Box 3, Folder 73)
  - Klondike diary chronology, typescript (Box 3, Folder 74)
  - Research notes on the Yukon
    - Notes from "Along Alaska's Great River" by Schwatka, typescript, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 75)
    - Notes from "Early Days on the Yukon" by W. Ogilvie, typescript, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 76)
    - Notes from Hudson Stuck's "Voyages on the Yukon and its Tributaries," typescript (Box 3, Folder 77)
    - "The Klondike Discovery" by Dr. A. E. Wills (acting mining recorder at Forty Mile), printed article, 1923 Feb 17 (Box 3, Folder 78)
      From Engineering and Mining Journal-Press
  - Draft chapters on the Klondike and Yukon Country
    - "Robert Campbell, at Fort Selkirk, as early as 1850 [...]," typescript, corrected, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 79)
    - "Vanity is often the unseen spur," typescript, corrected, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 80)
    - "But, O vain boast!/Who can control his fate?", typescript, corrected, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 81)
    - "1. The handful of claimholders [...]," manuscript and typescript carbon, corrected (Box 3, Folder 82)
    - "The White Pass," typescript, corrected, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 83)
    - "Chap III. The Yukon has its beginning [...]," manuscript, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 84)
    - "1. Down Lakes and River," manuscript and typescript, corrected (Box 3, Folder 85)
    - "The Klondike Rush of 1897," typescript of three chapters, corrected (Box 3, Folder 86)
      Includes "The White Horse Pass Trail" and "Down Lakes and River"
    - "Dawson," typescript, corrected, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 87)
    - "Life in Dawson," manuscript (Box 3, Folder 88)
    - "The Arrival of the Cheechakos," typescript, corrected, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 89)
    - "Jack London," typescript, corrected (Box 3, Folder 90)
    - "The Diggings," typescript, corrected, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 91)
    - "The Northwest Mounted Police," typescript, corrected and typescript carbon, uncorrected (Box 3, Folder 92)
  - Newspaper articles by MB about mining in Idaho and Nevada, mounted, with manuscript annotations, 1902-05 (Box 3, Folder 93)
  - Stikine River diary transcript, carbon typescript, corrected, [1911] (Box 3, Folder 94)
  - Newspaper article by MB about Pancho Villa, from the Sun, with manuscript corrections, 1919 Apr 20 (Box Bsd, folder 95)
  - Diary of trip to Lincoln County, New Mexico to interview associates of Billy the Kid, 1926
    See: Box 4, folder 111
  - "Bmali of the Lurio," short story, 1927
    See: Box 1, folder 12
- Other Papers, 1897-1974; Series III; 3; (1 volume)
  - Contract between MB and L. W. Fox, Dawson City, N.W.T., witnessed by Jack London and Louis W. Bond, 1897 Nov 18 (Box 3, Folder 96)
    With account sheet for 1897, audited by Fox 1898 Jul 19
  - Maps of the Yukon Territory and Alaska, 1905-09 (Box Bsd, folder 97)
    Two Canada Geologic Survey maps, one of the Yukon Territory and one showing auriferous gravels on Bonanza and Hunter Creeks, and one USGS map showing areas affected by an 1899 earthquake near Yakutat Bay
  - Skidoo Gold Mines, Summary of General Report, typescript carbon, 1915 (Box 3, Folder 98)
  - "Candelabria de Dios," article by Oliver H. P. La Farge, typescript carbon (Box 3, Folder 99)
  - Adventures with Peons, Princes and Tycoons by Marshall Bond, Jr., bound typescript with photographs, [1974] (Box 4)
    Published in 1983 by Star Rover House, Oakland, California
- Photographs, 1888-1926; Series IV; 0.54; (1 box) + 1 volume
  Arranged chronologically.
  - MB at Yale, 1888 (Box 5, Folder 100)
  - "Our Klondike cabin," shows MB, Oliver H. P. La Farge, Stanley Pearce, Lyman Colt, and dogs Jack ("Buck") and Pat, 1898 (Box 5, Folder 101)
    Two contemporary photos, one with the dogs, one without, and three later copies of the one including the dogs; one of these copies, dated 1908, is autographed by Jack London, and the other two are copies of the autographed copy
  - Commercially produced photographs of the Klondike region and Dawson
    - E. A. Hegg, 32 views of Chilkoot Pass, Klondike River, and Dawson, signed in the negative, 1898-1904 (Box 5, Folder 102-103)